Raphael Soyer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Writings & Notes, circa 1946-1987, Series 3:; (Box 2-3; 1.5 linear feet)
  - Writings & Notes by Soyer, circa 1946-1987, Subseries 3.1:
    Among the writings and notes by Soyer are his writings about artists, primarily draft essays for articles and introductions of exhibition catalogs. Artists written about include Benny Andrews, Jacques Lipchitz, Alice Neel, and others. Additional writings by Soyer include drafts of book reviews, and drafts of articles, essays, and lectures about his life, his artwork, and the social realism art movement.
    Also found are drafts, notes, typescripts, journals, and galley proofs for Soyer's four published books A Painter's Pilgrimage (1962), Homage to Thomas Eakins (1966), Self-Revealment: a Memoir (1969), and Diary of an Artist (1977). Also among the writings by Soyer are 13 of his engagement calendars and other miscellaneous notes.
    Most of Soyer's writings have been scanned, except for repetitive drafts and incomplete repetitive manuscripts and galley proofs of his published books. Early drafts of published books have been scanned.
    - Writings about Artists, circa 1950-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Book Reviews, circa 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Articles, Essays, and Lectures, circa 1946-1987, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Material concerning Diary of an Artist, 1965-1976, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-23)
    - Incomplete Draft Typescripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966, (5 folders; not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 24-28)
    - Notes for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 29-32)
    - Incomplete Draft Typescripts for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962, (6 folders; not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 33-38)
    - Galley Proofs for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962, (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Notes and Manuscripts for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-43)
    - Early Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-46)
    - Second Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (6 folders; not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 47-52)
    - Second Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Third Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
    - Galley Proofs for Self Revealment, 1966-1969, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1967, 1971-1979, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-12)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1981, 1983, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writings & Notes by Others, 1953-1984, Subseries 3.2:
    Writings and notes by others include various draft typescripts of essays, articles, and one dissertation about various artists and art movements written by art scholars. Most of these essays appear to have been sent to Soyer for his review and opinion. Also found are a few short essays about Soyer. Additional items of note are draft articles written by artists for Reality magazine, for which Soyer was an editor.
    This subseries has not been scanned.
    - John Baker, "Guy Pene Du Bois on Realism," 1977, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - William Benton, "Reginald Marsh as I Remember Him," circa 1955, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - William H. Gerdts, "Werner Groshans and His Art," circa 1981, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Patricia Hills, Review of Serge Guilbaut, How New York Stole The Idea of Modern Art, 1984, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Patricia Hills, "The Socially Concerned Painters of the 1930s," 1982, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Patricia Hills, "Social Concern and Urban Realism: American Painting in the 1930s," 1981, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Norma Nichols, Dissertation, The Mirrors of Eve: Changing Images of Women in American Art, 1670-1980, 1982, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - Frances M. Wilson, Essay about Soyer's Homage to Thomas Eakins, 1970, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Writings about Soyer, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Articles & Notes for Reality, 1953-1955, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - Poetry, 1958-circa 1970s, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1954, circa 1970s-1980s, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Legal & Financial Records, 1959-1988, Series 4:; (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scattered legal and financial records include two account books, bank statements, receipts, and invoices. Documents related to the publishing of Soyer's books include contracts with the publishers and royalty statements. Additional items found here are consignment lists and loan agreements with art museums and galleries for the exhibition of his work.
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder. Account books, bank statements, and receipts and invoices have not been scanned.
  - Account Books, 1962-1988, (2 books; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Bank Statements, 1968, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Consignment Lists & Loan Agreements, 1962-1987, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
  - Contracts, 1959-1982, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
  - Leases, 1966-1985 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Receipts & Invoices, 1964, 1970-1987, (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Royalty Statements, 1968-1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, 1933-1989, Series 5:; (Box 3-4; 0.3 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of catalogs and announcements for exhibitions of Raphael Soyer's artwork and the artwork of others; numerous news clippings about Soyer, his exhibitions, publication of his books, and about realist painters; and a few articles written by Soyer. Other scattered items include brochures and press releases about art events, page proofs for Soyer's writings, and reproductions of his artwork. There are three issues of the journal Reality, of which Soyer was an editor.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned, except for a few extant brochures, entire magazines, scattered page proofs, and reproductions of artwork by Soyer and others.
  - Catalogs & Exhibition Announcements, 1941-1979 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1933-1976, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 41-47)
  - Clippings, 1977-1989, (8 folders) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 1-8)
  - Undated Clippings, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 4 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Booklet, "The Germans Got Madder and Madder" (Illustrated by Soyer), 1944, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Brochures, 1944-1982, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Business Cards, circa 1950-1987 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Magazines, 1976, 1987, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Page Proofs, Raphael Soyer: Life Drawings and Portraits, 1986, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Page Proofs, Miscellaneous, circa 1970s, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Press Releases, 1954, 1979-1981 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Reality Journal, 1953-1955 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 17)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Soyer, circa 1960s-1980s, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, circa 1950s-1970s, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 19)
- Photographs, circa 1953-1987, Series 6:; (Box 5, OV 6; 0.5 linear feet)
  Photographs depict Soyer painting portraits and drawing in his studio, with his wife Rebecca and with unidentified friends, with fellow artist Jose De Creeft after painting De Creeft's portrait, with his friend Isaac Bashevis Singer, and in the process of painting a portrait of Gross and his wife. Photographs of other artists include Chaim Gross, Edward Hopper, Joseph Floch, and Moses Soyer.
  Also found are photographs of art events, including gallery receptions, many of which are unidentified and undated. Many of the photographs of gallery receptions depict Soyer with artists including Jose De Creeft, Chaim Gross, Rudolf Baranik, David Burliuk, R. B. Kitaj, Leon Kroll, Jacob Lawrence, Jack Levine, Reuben Nakian, Alice Neel, and others. Also found are a few photographs of Soyer's artwork and artwork by others.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety, except for photographs of artwork by Soyer and others. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer in His Studio, 1969-circa 1980, (Oversized photographs housed in OV 6) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Wife Rebecca & Friends, 1964-1983 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Jose De Creeft, circa 1970s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Isaac Singer, circa early 1970s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Photograph of Joseph Floch, circa 1970s, (Housed in OV 6) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Chaim Gross, 1974-1982, (Oversized photographs housed in OV 6) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Edward Hopper, circa 1953 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Moses Soyer, circa early 1970s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Photograph of Model, Eliza, 1987 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer at Unidentifed Conference, circa 1960s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Presentation of Soyer's Portrait of Golda Meir to National Portrait Gallery, 1975 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Reception for Isaac Singer, circa 1978 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Birthday Party for Soyer (possibly at Hirshhorn Museum), circa 1980 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Associated American Artists Galleries, 1967 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception (possibly at the Whitney Museum), 1967 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception (possibly at the Forum Gallery), circa early 1970s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Gallery Receptions, Early 1970s-1982, (2 folders) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 17-18)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Hirshhorn Gallery, 1982 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Forum Gallery, 1982 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 20)
  - Photograph of Unidentified People, circa 1980s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Gallery Installations, 1966, circa 1970s (Box 5 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Works by Raphael Soyer, 1974-1975, (Not scanned) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Works by Others, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Oversize Photographs of Raphael Soyer in His Studio, 1975-circa 1980, (Scanned with Box 5, F1) (Box OV 6)
  - Oversize Photograph of Joseph Floch, circa 1970s, (Scanned with Box 5, F5) (Box OV 6)
  - Oversize Photograph of Chaim Gross, 1974-1982, (Scanned with Box 5, F6) (Box OV 6)
- Artwork, 1968, undated, Series 7:; (Box 5; 2 folders)
  Artwork found in this collection includes one undated pencil sketch by an unidentified artist and a facsimile of a 1968 sketchbook belonging to Raphael Soyer which documents his time traveling through Europe. This facsimile was produced by the Forum Gallery as a limited edition in 1968.
  - Sketch, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 25)
  - Raphael Soyer: A 1968 Sketchbook (Facsimile), 1968 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 26)